Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) Records
Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) Records
1950-2002
1970-1985
Commission of Professors of Adult Education
9 linear ft.
Organizational records (correspondence, financial papers, legal papers, documentation of conferences and other meetings, membership files, reports, task force and committee papers, and printed material) of the Commission of Professors of Adult Education. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include Robert A. Carlson, Mary Jane Even, William Griffith, Cyril Orvin Houle, Roy John Ingham, Malcolm Shepherd Knowles, Alan Boyd Knox, Howard McClusky, Wayne Schroeder and Wilson B. Thiede. Also present are subject files for organizations including the Adult Education Association, the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, the Association of University Evening Colleges, the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, the National Association for Public and Continuing Education, and the National University Extension Association. There are also general and regional printed materials as well as some audio-visual materials (film, slides, and tape recordings).
149333
Biographical History
The Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) was established in 1959 as a division of what is now the American Association of Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE). CPAE’s purposes are to support graduate professional adult education, to increase the relevance and quality of dissertations in the field, and to encourage and support professional adult education research.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) Records contains material specific to the Commission and also material from other organizations in the adult education field. The collection is divided into four series. Organizational records includes correspondence, financial and legal papers, meetings documentation, membership files, reports, task force and committee papers, and printed material. Subject files comprises material on various other organizations and institutions, ranging from the African Adult Education Association to Wayne State University. Printed material (divided into General and Regional) contains studies, reports, brochures, directories, and other similar material. Audiovisual material contains a film, several trays of slides from conferences and workshops (one in China), 100 cassette tapes from the 1980 National Adult Education Conference, and a number of reel-to-reel tapes of interviews with deans and directors of 20 different adult education programs, both traditional and alternative.
Several well-known adult educators are strongly represented in both Correspondence and Printed material: Robert A. Carlson, Mary Jane Even, William Griffith, Cyril Houle, Ray Ingham, Malcolm S. Knowles, Alan Boyd Knox, Howard McClusky, Wayne Schroeder, and Wilson B. Thiede.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically and is not sorted by correspondent. Subject files are arranged alphabetically. Printed material is further divided into General, arranged alphabetically by publication title, and Regional, arranged alphabetically by name of region. Audiovisual (AV) material -- cassette tapes, reel-to-reel tapes, and computer disks -- has been placed together in one box; AV items that have a logical location in the collection structure are listed there as well as under Audiovisual material. For example, the audiotape of the 1999 CPAE business meeting is listed under Audiovisual material > Tapes > CPAE business meeting 1999 and also under Organizational Records > Meetings > Business > Tape of business meeting, 1999.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections.
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Carlson, Robert A.; Houle, Cyril Orvin, 1913-; Ingham, Roy John, 1925-; Knowles, Malcolm Shepherd, 1913-; Knox, Alan Boyd, 1931-; Even, Mary Jane.; Griffith, William S.; McClusky, Howard, 1900-1982.; Schroeder, Wayne.; Thiede, Wilson B.; Adult Education Association.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; American Association for Adult Education; Association of University Evening Colleges (U.S.); Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; Commission of Professors of Adult Education -- Archives.; Commission of Professors of Adult Education -- Records and correspondence.; National University Extension Association.; National Association for Public Continuing & Adult Education.; Adult education.; Adult education -- North America.; Agendas (administrative records); Annual reports.; Audiocassettes.; Correspondence.; Film reels.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Reports.; Slides (photographs); Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Commission of Professors of Adult Education, 1981-2006.
Inventory
- Organizational records
  - Correspondence
    - Jan 1963 - Mar 1973, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - Apr 1973 - Jun 1978, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - Jul 1978 - Dec 1982, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Jan 1983 - Dec 1996, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - 1997 - 2001 (Box 5)
  - Dissertation directory proposal, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Financial papers
    - Budgets, 1978-1983; 1992-1996 (Box 5)
    - Checking and savings accounts, 1980-1984; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Internal accounting records, 1980-1983; 1991-1995; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Invoices, 1979-1984 (Box 5)
    - Invoices, 1979-1984 (Box 5)
    - Tax material, 1984; 1992 (Box 5)
    - Treasurer's reports, 1984-1999; 2001 (Box 5)
  - Legal papers
    - Constitutions and bylaws, 1980; 1987,; 1999-2001,; undated (Box 5)
    - Constitutions and ratification ballots, 1976 (Box 6)
  - Meetings
    - Annual
      - 1965-1977, 13 folders (Box 6)
      - 1978-1985, 1987-1993, 15 folders (Box 7)
      - 1994-1996, 1999-2002, 7 folders (Box 8)
      - Audiotape of 2000 annual meeting, 2 audiocassettes (Box 17)
    - Business
      - 1964-1966, 1987-2001, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Audiotape of 1999 business meeting, 1 audiocassette (Box 17)
    - Executive committee, 1968; 1973,; 1979,; 1984-1988,; 1991,; 1994,; 1999-2001; 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Membership files
    - Directories
      - 1960-1683, 3 folders (Box 8)
      - 1984-2002, undated, 4 folders (Box 9)
    - Forms and form letters (Box 9)
    - Membership reports, 1980s and 1990s (Box 9)
    - Reminder letters, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Photographs, 1961; 1977 (Box 9)
  - Reports
    - Annual, 1975; 1982; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Doctorates conferred in adult education, 1988, 1989 (Box 9)
    - Progress, 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Task forces and committees
    - Rosters, 1978; 2000-2002,; undated (Box 9)
    - Archives, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Awards, 1998; undated (Box 9)
    - "Black Book" editor search committee, 1988 (Box 9)
    - Certification, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Community Education, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Extension, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - External Degree, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Field Experience, 1977-1979 (Box 9)
    - Future of CPAE, 1992; 1995,; 2002 (Box 9)
    - Futures of adult education graduate programs, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Instructional Improvement, 1977-1978; 1994-1995 (Box 10)
    - International, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Lifelong Learning, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Membership, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Needed Research, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - Promotion and Tenure, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Theory Building, 1967-1969; 1977-1979 (Box 10)
    - University Politics, 1977-1979 (Box 10)
  - Printed material, material published or printed by CPAE
    - Brochures, 1977; 1979,; 1982,; undated (Box 10)
    - Development and Dissemination of Adult Education Knowledge Theory and Research, 1978; grant proposal to National Institute of Education (Box 10)
    - Directory of adult education graduate programs in North America, 1998 (Box 10)
    - Directory of professional colleagues, 1998; 2000,; 2001 (Box 10)
    - From Movement to Profession: History of the Adult Education Profession in the United States with Emphasis on the Commission of Professors of Adult Education (Robert A. Carlson), 1972 (Box 10)
    - From Movement to Profession: Documentation of the Developing Professional Nature of Adult Education in North America (Robert A. Carlson), 1973 (Box 10)
    - Graduate programs in adult education in the Unied States and Canada, 1986 (Box 10)
    - Newsletter
      - 1975-1999, 5 folders (Box 10)
      - 2000-2002 (Box 11)
    - Problems of Graduate Education Designs (Wilson B. Thiede, John Ohliger, Clive C. Veri), 1973 (Box 11)
    - Professional Exchange Program Data, 1969 (Box 11)
    - Registry of Professional and Research Interests, 1982 (Box 11)
    - Report of a survey of CPAE structure and member services, 1992 (Box 11)
    - Skill Bank Report, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Some Epistemotological Considerations for Adult Education, ca. 1973 (Box 11)
    - Standards for graduate programs in adult education, undated (Box 11)
    - Strategies for strengthening support for adult education graduate programs on university campuses, 1994 (Box 11)
    - Strengthening universitysupport for adult education graduate programs on campuses, 1993 (Box 11)
    - Suggestions for Future Activities of the Commission, undated (Box 11)
    - Trends and Issues in Graduate Programs in Adult Education (Mary Jane Even), 1975 (Box 11)
    - Tribute to Professor Robert M. Smith, undated (Box 11)
    - What's New Newsletters, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11)
- Subject files (non-CPAE)
  This series contains material related to organizations other than the CPAE. The bulk consists of printed material (brochures, newsletters, pamphlets, papers, reports, etc).
  - Adult Education Association of the U.S.A., 14 folders (Box 11, 12)
  - Adult Education Association of Wisconsin, 1971 (Box 12)
  - Adult Education Foundation of Akron, 1953-1956; undated; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Adult Education Resource Center, 1973 (Box 12)
  - African Adult Education Association, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Akron Area Adult Education Council, undated (Box 12)
  - American Association of Adult and Continuing Education, 1982-1983; 2 folders (Box 12)
  - American Association of Junior Colleges, 1969 (Box 12)
  - American Foundation for Continuing Education, undated (Box 12)
  - American Foundation for Political Education, 1955 (Box 12)
  - American Pharmaceutical Association, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Association of University Evening Colleges, 1967-1969; newsletter, material from 27th annual meeting, paper "Higher adult education: its present and future" (Philip E. Frandson); 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Brooklyn College, 1968-1969 (Box 12)
  - Center for Studies of Leisure, 1971 (Box 12)
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults, 1958-1968; newsletter, pamphlets; 7 folders (Box 12)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations, 1974 (Box 12)
  - Commission on Research, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Commission on the Humanities, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Committee of Adult Education Organizations, 1967-1969 (Box 13)
  - Educational Resources Information Center/Adult Education (ERIC/AE), 1968-1973; undated; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Fund for Adult Education, 1953-1956; undated; annual reports, 1956 Perkins Lectures; 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Galaxy Conference, 31st Annual, 1969 (Box 13)
  - Institute for Administrative Advancement, 1975 (Box 13)
  - Institute for Civic Education, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Institute for Research on Training, 1980 (Box 13)
  - International Congress of University Adult Education (ICUAE), 1970 (Box 13)
  - Marquette University, 1961 (Box 13)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, Art Seminars in the Home, undated (Box 13)
  - National Adult Education Conference, 1981, 1982 (Box 13)
  - National Advisory Council on Adult Education, 1982 (Box 13)
  - National Association for Public and Continuing Adult Education (NAPCAE), 1975-1976 (Box 13)
  - National Board on Graduate Education, ca. 1974 (Box 13)
  - National Broadcasting Company, "Science and greasepaint", undated (Box 13)
  - National University Continuing Education Association (NUCEA), 1982 (Box 13)
  - National University Extension Association, 1970; 1972,; 1979,; 1980,; newsletters, 1980 regional meeting; 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Northwest Adult Education Association, 1974 (Box 13)
  - Research Training Institute in Adult Education, 1967 (Box 13)
  - Resources for Educators of Adults, 1979 (Box 13)
  - SCUTREA, 1982 (Box 13)
  - Syracuse University, University College, 1960s (Box 13)
  - UNESCO, 1981; adult education directories list (Box 13)
  - University of Akron, 1956 (Box 14)
  - University of Chicago, 1957; 1959 (Box 14)
  - University of Guelph, 1976 (Box 14)
  - University of Mid-America, ca. 1978-1979 (Box 14)
  - University of Saskatchewan, 1974; 1976 (Box 14)
  - University of Wisconsin, Madison, 1995 (Box 14)
  - University of Wyoming, 1974 (Box 14)
  - Virginia Tech, 1994; College of Education restructuring proposal (Box 14)
  - Washington University, 1965 (Box 14)
  - Wayne State University, 1970 (Box 14)
- Printed material (non-CPAE)
  - General
    - Adult Basic Education National Teacher Training Study, 1972 (Box 14)
    - Adult Education Publication Advertisements, undated (Box 14)
    - Adventure and the Emerging Roles of the Adult Education Leader (Howard McClusky), undated (Box 14)
    - Careers in Adult and Continuing Education, undated (Box 14)
    - Comparative Adult Education Newsletter, v. 1, no. 1, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Continuous and Integrated Education of the Adult as Observed in Industrial Education Programs (R. Rowray), undated (Box 14)
    - Draper Fund Report, no. 9, 1980 (Box 14)
    - Educational programs for educators of adults, 1981 (Box 14)
    - Graduate Programs in Adult Education Directory, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Graduate Programs in Adult Education Survey, 1976 (Box 14)
    - International Adult Education Exchange and Cooperation Directory, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Part-Time Professors of Adult Education Directories, 1970s (Box 14)
    - Projections of Extension-Adult Education into the Next Decade (J. Paul Leagans), 1966 (Box 14)
    - RFD Delivery System Overview, undated (Box 14)
    - What is "Research" in Adult Education? Issues in Methodological Diversity (David C. Williams), 1977 (Box 14)
  - Regional
    - California, 1950s-1960s (Box 14)
    - Colorado, 1980 (Box 14)
    - Indiana, ca. 1959 (Box 14)
    - Massachusetts, 1970s (Box 14)
    - New York, undated (Box 14)
    - Texas, undated (Box 14)
    - United States, 1960s (Box 14)
    - Canada, 1978; 1987,; undated (Box 14)
- Audiovisual material
  - Film (35mm?) - "Quest for Peace", 1962; 2 reels (Reel 1, 2)
  - Slides, AEA/NAPCAE conference (1975); China; workshops; THIS BOX MISSING AS OF JAN 2007 (MRC) (Box -)
  - Tapes
    - National Adult Education Conference, 1980; 100 audiocassettes (Box 15)
    - CPAE annual meeting, 2000; 2 audiocassettes (Box 17)
    - CPAE business meeting, 1999; 1 audiocassette (Box 17)
    - Account of Interview with Richard Poston and Dean Raymond Dey, Extension Division, Southern Illinois University, 1958; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Adrian, —, Community Development, University of Michigan, undated; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Anderson, — and Koenig, —, Community Development Specialists, University of Washington, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Bentley, Harold, Dean, Extension Division, University of Utah, 19 May 1958; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Bergevin, Paul, Professor of Adult Education, Indiana University, 8 May 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - (1) Career Counseling for Adults; (2) CEEB Session, S. Arbeiter and C. Aslanian, 15 Nov 1977; undated; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Chamberland, Martin, undated; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Child, Robert, Community Development Specialist, Southern Illinois University, 6 Apr 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Donohue, Maurice, Dean, University College, University of Chicago, 15 May 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Johnson, Eugene, Director of the Metroplex Assembly, Washington University, 5 Apr 1958; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Johnson, Kermit, Director of Evening College, Bradley University, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Miller, Harry, CSLEA, 22 Apr 1958; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Neville, Jake, Director of the Kellogg Center, Michigan State University, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Ogden, Jean, Co-author, These Things We've Tried, with Jess Ogden, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 16)
    - Pritchard, Carson, West Georgia College, 30 Apr [n.y.]; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Pritchard, Carson, Director of Community Education, Community Development, West Georgia College; Dr. Irvine S. Ingram, President of West Georgia College; and Miss English, associate of Mr. Pritchard, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Reed, Bernard, Administrator, Evening College, Cincinnati, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Schram, Wilbur, Dean, Extension Service, University of Washington, undated; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Thiede, Wilson B., Professor of Adult Education, University of Wisconsin, undated; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Zehmer, —, Dean, Extension Service, University of Virginia; and Fernback, —, Community Services, University of Virginia, 1957; 1 reel-to-reel tape (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous letters, electronic files, undated; 2 3-1/2" floppy disks, unknown format (Box 17)